"Should We Be Concerned About
Ochratoxin and Aflatoxin?"
Ochratoxin has been described
as toxic to the immune system,
developing fetus, kidneys,
nervous system, as well as
being carcinogenic—but
that’s in animal studies.
Ochratoxin causes kidney
toxicity in certain animal species,
but there is little documented
evidence of adverse effects in humans.
That’s why it’s only considered
a possible human carcinogen.
Big Ag assures that current
ochratoxin levels are safe
even among those who eat a
lot of contaminated foods.
The worst-case scenario may
be young children eating a lot
of oat-based cereals, but even then,
their lifetime cancer risk
is considered negligible,
with those arguing against
regulatory standards suggesting
you can eat more than
42 cups of oatmeal a day
and not worry about it.
Where do they get these
kinds of estimates?
They determine the so-called
benchmark dose in animals—
the dose of the toxin that
gives a 10% increase in pathology—
and then, because you want
to err on the side of caution,
you divide that dose by 500
as a kind of safety fudge factor
to develop the tolerable daily intake.
For cancer risk, you
can find the tumor dose—
the dose that increases
tumor incidence in lab animals
by 5%—and extrapolate down to
the ”negligible cancer risk intake,”
effectively incorporating
a 5,000-fold safety factor.
It seems kind of arbitrary, right?
But what else are you going to do?
You can’t just intentionally feed people
the stuff and see what happens.
Though look, people eat
it all the time.
Can’t we just follow people and
their diets out over time
and see if people who eat more
whole grains like oats, for example,
are more likely to have
cancer or live shorter lives?
What is the association
between whole grain intake
and all-cause, cardiovascular,
and cancer mortality?
Every additional ounce of whole
grains a day is associated with
not only a lower risk for
cancer but also a lower risk
of dying from all
causes put together.
Here are all the big cancer studies.
Every single one, if anything,
trended towards lower cancer risk.
Bottom line is that you
don’t find adverse effects
confirmed in these population studies.
This is not to say ochratoxin
is necessarily harmless,
but any such risk it
does pose doesn’t outweigh
the known beneﬁts of
whole grain consumption.
In fact, healthy constituents of
the whole grains themselves
like the antioxidants may
directly reduce the impacts
of mycotoxins by protecting
cells from damage,
so eating lots of fruits and
vegetables may also help.
Either way, a healthy diet
can play a signiﬁcant role
in mitigating the risk.
In summary, healthy foods
like whole grains are good,
but just not as good as they
could be because of ochratoxin;
whereas less healthful foods,
like wine and pork,
are worse because of the mycotoxin.
Ochratoxin was detected, for example,
in 44% of tested pork.
In recent years, mold has
been blamed for all sorts
of vague subjective symptoms, but
we have little scientific evidence
that mold has anything
to do with them.
However, this concept of
“toxic mold syndrome” has permeated
the public consciousness, perpetuated
by disreputable predatory practices,
by those making money testing
homes for mold spores or
testing people’s urine or blood.
But all these tests are said to just
further propagate misinformation
and inflict unnecessary,
and often exorbitant costs
on patients desperate for a diagnosis.
“The continued belief in this myth
is perpetuated by those charlatans
who believe that measles vaccines
cause autism, that homeopathy works,
that fluoride in the water
should be removed . . .”
Mold toxin contamination of
food, however, has emerged
as a legitimate issue
of serious concern,
perhaps even more important
than other contaminants
that might make their way
into the food supply.
Hundreds of different types have
been identified, but only one has been
classified as a known human
carcinogen, and that’s aflatoxin.
The ochratoxin I talked about before
is a possible human carcinogen,
but we know aflatoxin causes
cancer in human beings.
In fact, aﬂatoxins are amongst
the most powerful
carcinogens we know about.
For example, it has been
estimated that about a fifth of all
liver cancer cases may be
attributable to aflatoxins,
and since liver cancer is
the third-leading cause of
cancer deaths worldwide, and
kills so rapidly after diagnosis,
the contribution of aflatoxins to
this deadly cancer is quite significant.
And once it makes it into
the food, there is almost nothing
you can do to remove it.
Cooking, for example, doesn’t help.
So, once it makes it into crops,
or the meat, dairy, and eggs
from animals consuming
those crops, it’s too late.
So, we have to prevent contamination
in the first place,
and that’s what we’ve been doing
for decades in this country.
Because of government regulations,
companies are almost
“always sampling” for aflatoxin,
resulting in nearly a billion dollars
in losses every year, which may
get worse if climate change worsens
aflatoxin contamination
in the Midwest Corn Belt.
So, on a consumer level it’s really
more of a public health problem
in the less industrialized
world such as African countries
where conditions are ripe,
and farmers can’t afford
to throw away a billion
dollars’ worth of crops.
Indeed, aflatoxin remains a
public health threat in Africa,
rural China, and Southeast Asia,
affecting more than half of humanity,
which explains why the prevalence
of liver cancer in those areas
may be 30 times higher, but it is not
a major problem in the U.S. or Europe.
For example, only about 1% of
Americans have detectible levels
of aflatoxins in their bloodstream.
Why even 1%, though?
Well, the FDA works to ensure
that the levels of exposure
to these toxins are not
kept as low as possible,
but, instead, as low as practical.
For example, in California there
has been an increase in unacceptable
aflatoxin levels in pistachios,
almonds, and figs.
Unacceptable in Europe, that is,
so it affects our ability to export,
but not necessarily unacceptable
for U.S. consumers,
as we allow twice as much
aflatoxin contamination.
Figs are unique since they’re
allowed to dry on the tree.
This makes them particularly
susceptible to aﬂatoxin production.
It would be interesting to know
about the fig consuming habits
of the 1% of Americans who
turned up positive for the toxin.
If figs were to blame, I’d
encourage people to diversify
their dried fruit consumption,
but nuts are so good for us
that we really want to
keep them in our diets.
The cardiovascular health beneﬁts
outweigh the carcinogenic effects,
preventing thousands of
strokes and heart attacks
for every one case of liver cancer.
“Thus, the population health beneﬁts
provided by increased nut consumption
clearly outweigh the risks associated
with increased aﬂatoxin exposure.”
So, we’re left with aflatoxin
being mostly a problem
in the developing world, and
because of that, it remains
a largely and rather shamefully
ignored global health issue.
Where attention has been paid,
it has been largely driven
by the need to meet stringent import
regulations in the richer nations
of the world rather than to
protect the billions of people
exposed on a daily basis.